A Guide to the Reaumur C. Stearnes Papers 1830-1942
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Reaumur C. Stearnes Papers 1830-1942
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2547 and I835
This collection consists of ca. 20,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Reaumur C. Stearnes Papers were a gift to the Library by Mrs. Reamur C. Stearnes of Hempstead, Long Island, New York, on November 12, 1946.
Biographical/Historical Information
Reaumur Coleman Stearnes was born on April 8, 1866 in Dublin, Pulaski County, Virginia, the son of Dr. John Lewis and Phoebe Ann (nee McDermed) Stearnes. He won Greek and philosophy medals from the University of Richmond and was graduated in 1887 as valedictorian of his class. He married Mary Elizabeth Arnold in 1888. During the period 1888-1906, he taught mathematics and science at Allegheny Institute, Roanoke; was division superintendent of public schools for Roanoke County; practiced law at Salem; and helped organize the Cooperative Education Association and the Virginia State Teachers' Association, of which he served as president from 1901 to 1906.
Stearnes was appointed secretary to the State Board of Education in 1906. In 1913, upon the resignation of Dr. Joseph E. Eggleston, he was appointed Superintendent of Public Instruction. He was elected to the position in 1914 and served until 1918 when he lost a re-election bid. During World War I he served in various capacities for the War Camp Community Service in Atlanta, Georgia. From 1922 to 1925 he attended Columbia University, receiving an MA degree. He taught mathematics at New York University and Stony Brook School from 1925 to 1939. He also lectured on business administration and secretarial studies at Merchants and Bankers' Business and Secretarial School, New York. In 1936, at age 70, Stearnes earned a Ph.D. degree from New York University.
Stearnes was a member of the Sons of the American Revolution, Phi Delta Kappa, Phi Delta Theta, Pi Mu Epsilon, and was a thirty-third degree Mason and Grand Secretary of the Royal Arcanum Lodge. Reaumur C. Stearnes died in New York City on May 25, 1946, and was buried in Dublin, Pulaski County, Virginia.
A doctoral dissertation entitled "The Life and Administration of Reaumur Coleman Stearnes" by Vearl G. McBride is available in the University of Virginia Library.
Scope and Content Information
The Reaumur Coleman Stearnes Papers consist chiefly of correspondence, bound volumes, financial and legal papers, reports, newspaper clippings, printed materials, photographs and memorabilia. The papers pertain to Stearnes' life and his career in public education and especially relate to his service as secretary of the Virginia State Board of Education, 1906-1913, as Superintendent of Public Instruction, 1913- 1918, and in various capacities for the War Camp Community Service, 1918-1922. Topics of interest in the correspondence pertaining to education include: textbook adoption, certification of teachers, courses of study, and his bid for re-election as Superintendent of Public Instructions. Other topics for which there is material include citizen efforts to run recreational activities in Georgia during World War I, local political campaigns, and family and personal matters, particularly his teaching, and futher education at New York University.
As secretary to the State Board of Education and Superintendent of Public Instruction, Stearnes reviewed the credentials of physicians who intended to practice in Virginia to be certain they met a requirement of four years of high school. The political, social, religious and racial implications of his decisions are documented in the correspondence and related papers pertaining to the topic. Considerable information on the candidates for certification is also present.
Financial and legal papers chiefly pertain to Stearnes' business transactions, his career as a lawyer, and to the Stearnes family itself.
Prominent correspondents include: Edwin Anderson Alderman, Paul B. Barringer, R. F. Boatwright, William Cabell Bruce, Harry F. Byrd, Sr., T. A. Cairns, Charles Corbin, Arthur Kyle Davis, George S. Denny, Murray T. Edwards, James Taylor Ellyson, W. S. Gooch, Garrard Harris, T. W. Harrison, W. E. Hatcher, Herbert Hoover, J. L. Jarman, W. H Keister, J. P. McConnell, H. R. McIlwaine, Thomas R. Marshall, Thomas S. Martin, Mary Cooke Branch Munford, Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., Mary Newton Stanard, Claude A. Swanson, William Howard Taft, and Woodrow Wilson.
Organization
The collection is divided into nine series: I. Correspondence; II. Financial and Legal Papers; III. Superintendent of Public Instruction Papers; IV. War Camp Community Service Papers; V. Personal Education Papers; VI. Topical Files; VII. Printed Material; VIII. Bound Volumes; and IX. Over and Undersized Items, Memorabilia, etc. Folders are arranged chronologically within each series. Series I (Boxes 1-18) consists of general correspondence followed by topical correspondence. Series II (Boxes 18-25) is arranged in the same manner; boxes 23-25 contain miscellaneous receipts. Series III (Boxes 26-34) contains papers relating to his campaign efforts for re-election as Superintendent including petitions from supporters on his behalf. Boxes 29-34 contain papers regarding his role in the certification of physicians who intended to practice in Virginia provided they met a four year high school requirement; boxes 31-34 contain papers regarding textbook adoption. Series IV (Boxes 34-38) chiefly consists of correspondence, reports, and miscellaneous papers pertaining to his work for the War Camp Community Service. Series V (Boxes 38-42) contains papers relating to Stearnes' teaching career, his work towards his doctorate and his interest in education. Series VI (Boxes 43-44) consists of various topical folders. Series VII (Boxes 44-46) contains printed material such as business and calling cards, letterheads, postcards, clippings, invitations, photographs, and speeches and essays. The bound volumes in Series VIII (Boxes 46-49) were numbered and filed chronologically; loose materials in the volumes were placed in inserts, numbered, and filed together in a single folder directly after the last of the bound volumes. Item-by-item listings of the bound volumes, oversize and other disparate materials in Series IX are included in the container list.
Contents List
- Series I: Corespondence
  - Correspondence 1890-1906 Jun (Box 1)
    5 folders
  - Correspondence 1906 Jul - 1909 May (Box 2)
    6 folders
  - Correspondence 1909 Jul - 1913 Jan 7 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1913 Jan 8 - 1914 Jan 24 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1914 Jan 26 - 1915 Aug (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1915 Sep - 1916 Sep (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1916 Oct - 1917 May 18 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1917 May 19 - Aug 10 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1917 Aug 11 - 1921 Feb (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1921 Mar - 1922 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1923 - 1925 Jun (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1925 Jul - 1929 Jun (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1929 Jul - 1933 Mar (Box 13)
    7 folders
  - Correspondence 1933 Apr - 1936 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence 1937 - 1941, 1950 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence n.d. (Box 16)
    2 folders
  - Correspondence re miscellaneous financial and legal matters 1868, 1895-1905 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence and related papers re Florida real estate 1895-1906 (Box 16)
  - Letters to R.C. Stearnes re receipts 1895-1942 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence and related papers re Royal Arcanum Lodge 1897, 1911-1938 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence and related papers - Paul Scherer 1901-1905 (Box 17)
  - Letters to R.C. Stearnes re miscellaneous legal matters 1903-1906 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence of R.C. Stearnes and T.A. Murphy 1903-1908 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence re March C. Renick 1904-1911 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence re Stearnes and Zeidler piano 1906-1909 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence between R.C. Stearnes and Claude A. Swanson 1913 (Box 17)
  - Letters of recommendation re R.C. Stearnes 1922-1938 (Box 18)
  - Letters to R.C. Stearnes from the American Trust Co. and the American National Bank 1924-1925 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence re Stearnes Family Finances 1931-1935 (Box 18)
  - Post Cards (having substantial messages) 1891-1941 (Box 18)
  - Christmas Cards (having substantial messages) 1904-1936, n.d. (Box 18)
- Series II: Financial and Legal Papers
  - Financial and Legal Papers 1861, 1873-1899 (Box 18)
  - Financial and Legal Papers 1900-1941, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Miscellaneous 1899-1938 (Box 20)
  - Receipts of Samuel Grice 1830-1895 (Box 20)
  - Legal Papers re Goff vs. Blankenship 1854, 1886, 1890, 1902-1904 (Box 20)
  - Legal Papers re Creston Land Co., Salem Land Co., and Henry's Rheumatic Remedy 1871, 1886, 1890-1905 (Box 20)
  - Legal Papers re T.D. Crawford and the Iron Belt Building and Loan Association 1883-1906 (Box 20)
  - Acid Iron Mineral Company 1886-1903, n.d. (Box 21)
    3 folders
  - Legal Papers re Real Estate 1891-1905 (Box 21)
  - Selected published records of Stearnes' court cases 1901-1906 (Box 21)
  - Legal Papers: Title to Lake Spring Land Co. Tract 1904 Aug 16 (Box 22)
  - Legal Papers re Thompson et. al. vs. Camper 1906 (Box 22)
  - Taxes 1919-1938 (Box 22)
  - Receipts re Richmond property 1922-1923 (Box 22)
  - Fenner and Beane 1927-1941 (Box 22)
  - Redman and Co. 1931-1934 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts 1899-1918 Jan (Box 23)
    unfoldered
  - Miscellaneous Receipts 1917 Nov - 1933 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts 1934-1944 (Box 25)
- Series III: Superintendent of Public Instruction Papers
  - Correspondence of R.C. Stearnes as Superintendent of Schools, Roanoke County 1830-1861, 1905-1912 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence and related papers of R.C. Stearnes as Superintendent of Public Instruction 1913-1918, n.d. (Box 26)
    4 folders
  - Correspondence re school conditions 1914 (Box 27)
  - Letters to R.C. Stearnes from School Superintendents 1914 Nov 16 - Dec 5 (Box 27)
  - Courses of study for Roanoke County Schools 1893-1894 (Box 27)
  - Annual Financial Reports Division Superintendent of Schools ca. 1913-1918 (Box 27)
  - Superintendent of Public Instruction: Weekly Activities 1914-1918 (Box 27)
  - Minutes of the Virginia State Board of Education 1914-1918 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence re campaign for Superintendent of Public Instruction 1916 Jun - Jul (Box 27)
  - Correspondence re campaign for Superintendent of Public Instruction 1916 Aug - 1917 Aug (Box 28)
  - Campaign for Superintendents of Public Instruction: Miscellaneous Papers 1916-1917 (Box 28)
  - Superintendent of Public Instruction: Nomination Petitions 1917 May - Jun, n.d. (Box 28)
  - Petitioners requesting RCS to be a candidate for Superintendent of Public Instruction 1917 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence re Qualifying Certificates from State Board of Medical Examiners 1910 Aug - 1915 May (Box 29)
  - Correspondence re Qualifying Certificates from State Board of Medical Examiners 1915 Jun - 1916 Sep (Box 30)
    60 folders
  - Correspondence re Qualifying Certificates from State Board of Medical Examiners 1916 Oct - 1918 Mar, n.d. (Box 31)
  - Applications for Qualifying Certificates from State Board of Medical Examiners 1912-1916 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence and related papers re purchasing of textbooks for Virginia 1909-1916, n.d. (Box 31)
  - Correspondence re textbooks for Virginia school libraries: A-G 1910-1916 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence re textbooks for Virginia school libraries: H-Y 1910-1916 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence and reports re preferred list of textbooks 1912-1914 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence re textbooks in Virginia 1914-1918 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence re bids and price lists for public school library books 1917 Sep 27 - Oct 3 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence re bids and price lists for public school library books 1917 Oct 4 - Dec 7 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous papers re textbooks 1913-1918, n.d. (Box 33)
  - Reports to the State Board of Education re textbooks ca. 1914 (Box 33)
  - Reports re textbook sales in Virginia 1914-1915 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous price lists for school textbooks ca. 1914-1917 (Box 33)
  - Transcripts of testimony re Educational Publishing Co. in Virginia 1915 (Box 34)
  - Reports to State Senate of Virginia re school textbook selection 1916 (Box 34)
  - Textbook price lists n.d. (Box 34)
- Series IV: War Camp Community Service Papers
  - Correspondence re war effort campaign 1917-1918 (Box 34)
  - Correspondence chiefly re War Camp Community Service 1917, 1920 Jan - Nov (Box 34)
  - Correspondence chiefly re War Camp Community Service 1920 Dec - 1921 Dec (Box 35)
  - Correspondence and related papers re War Camp Community Service n.d. (Box 35)
  - War Camp Community Service: Daily Reports 1918 Mar - Jul (Box 35)
  - War Camp Community Service: Daily Reports 1918 Aug - 1920 Dec (Box 36)
  - War Camp Community Service Reports 1918-1920 (Box 36)
  - War Camp Community Service Reports and clippings 1921 (Box 37)
  - War Camp Community Service: Community Organizer's Weekly Reports 1919 May - 1920 Mar (Box 37)
  - War Camp Community Service: Community Organizer's Weekly Reports 1920 Apr - 1922 Jan (Box 38)
  - War Camp Community Service: Miscellaneous 1917-1926, n.d. (Box 38)
- Series V: Personal Education Papers
  - Letters and related papers chiefly re Virginia education 1904-1919, 1941-1942 (Box 38)
  - Class notes and related papers re New York University and other schools 1920-1924 (Box 38)
  - Class notes and related papers re New York University and other schools 1923-1938, n.d. (Box 39)
  - Additional Papers re Columbia University and New York University 1921-1939 (Box 40)
  - Stony Brook School: Miscellaneous Student Papers ca. 1925-1929 (Box 40)
  - Phi Delta Kappa 1926-1941 (Box 40)
  - Grade Books: New York University 1927-1939 (Box 40)
  - Student Examination Books: New York University 1934-1939 (Box 40)
  - Student Examination Books: New York University 1938-1939 (Box 41)
  - Merchants and Bankers' Business School: Tests and Projects 1931 (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous Examination Answers 1934 (Box 41)
  - Pedagogy 1887-1936, n.d. (Box 42)
  - Papers re Education 1904-1938, n.d. (Box 42)
  - Printed Materials re Education 1910-1917 (Box 42)
- Series VI: Topical Files
  - Index cards re miscellaneous subjects ca. 1906-1918 (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous Items 1908-1939 (Box 43)
  - Circulars and Memoranda 1913-1941, n.d. (Box 43)
  - Elections 1915-1941, n.d. (Box 43)
  - Sons of the American Revolution 1917-1941, n.d. (Box 43)
  - Papers re Casto-Craneo 1930-1942 (Box 43)
  - Papers re Casto-Craneo n.d. (Box 44)
  - Astor Lodge 1931-1939 (Box 44)
  - Stearnes Memorial ca. 1931 (Box 44)
  - Guardian Guardianship n.d. (Box 44)
- Series VII: Printed Material, Writings and Photographs
  - Business and Calling Cards 1890-1940 (Box 44)
  - Letterheads 1896-1920 (Box 44)
  - Speeches and Essays 1897-1918 (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous Invitations and Postcards 1902-1941 (Box 45)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1906-1938 (Box 45)
  - Membership cards of R.C. Stearnes 1909-1944 (Box 45)
  - Printed Material 1904-1922, 1924-1941 (Box 45)
  - Photographs (w/negatives) ca. 1890-1941 (Box 45)
  - Photographs: Proof Sheets ca. 1890-1941 (Box 45)
  - Photographs and Prints ca. 1890-1941 (Box 46)
- Series VIII: Bound Volumes
  - Memoranda book, "Notes on titles to School No. 11 in Central District" ca. 1891 (Box 46)
  - Memoranda book of R.C. Stearnes re miscellaneous legal matters ca. 1895 (Box 46)
  - Register of notes re deeds and legal matters ca. 1895 (Box 46)
  - Memoranda book of R.C. Stearnes re deeds and legal matters ca. 1895 (Box 46)
  - Register of deeds and legal matters ca. 1899 (Box 46)
  - Register of R.C. Stearnes re legal matters ca. 1900 (Box 46)
  - Register of deeds and legal matters 1905 (Box 47)
  - Ledger of R.C. Stearnes for a Business Education Course 1915-1917, 1922 (Box 47)
  - Journal of R.C. Stearnes for a Business Education Course 1915-1917, 1922 (Box 47)
  - Scrapbook of R.C. Stearnes' campaign for re-election as Superintendent of Public Instruction 1916-1920 (Box 47)
  - Journal of R.C. Stearnes for a Business Education course 1920 (Box 47)
  - Journal of R.C. Stearnes for a Business Education course 1920 (Box 47)
  - Notebook ca. 1921 (Box 48)
  - Notebook of R.C. Stearnes re mathematics and education ca. 1922-1925 (Box 48)
  - Class Roll Books, New York University 1929-1939 (Box 48)
    14 volumes
  - Class Role Books of R.C. Stearnes, Washington Heights School 1929-1939 (Box 48)
    6 volumes
  - Class Roll Books of R.C. Stearnes 1930-1932, n.d. (Box 48)
    3 volumes
  - Class Roll Books of R.C. Stearnes, Merchants and Bankers' School 1932-1938 (Box 48)
    4 volumes
  - Mathematics Notebook 1932-1934 (Box 48)
  - Mathematics Nnotebook 1936 (Box 49)
  - Latin notebook n.d. (Box 49)
  - Civics notebook, New York University n.d. (Box 49)
  - Papers pulled from volumes 6, 7, 8, 10, 13, and 35 1893-1912, 1922, 1931 (Box 49)
- Series IX: Over and Undersized Items, Memorabilia, etc.
  - Oversized Items
    - "Tenth Annual July Fourth Community Picnic..." 1920
    - Blueprints, revised plans of Roselawn, Henrico County, Virginia 1921 Mar 15
    - Map of a part of the Salem Improvement Company's property at Salem, Virginia n.d.
    - Map of property owned by Salem Club Land Co. n.d.
    - Map of the Riverside Land Company's property at Salem, Virginia n.d.
    - Map of the Washington Heights, property of the Washington Club Land Co., Roanoke, Virginia n.d.
  - Ledgers
    - I. Scrapbook of R.C. Stearnes 1912-1920
    - II. Scrapbook of R.C. Stearnes 1909, 1913-1917
    - III. Scrapbook of R.C. Stearnes 1913-1918
    - A. Record of results of examinations of applications for licenses to teach 1892-1896
    - B. Record of results of examinations of applications for licenses to teach 1897-1902
    - C. Record of results of examinations of applications for licenses to teach 1903-1905
  - Memorabilia
    Chiefly consists of ca. 42 pins and ribbons from various meetings, organizations and conventions; also included is a miniature bale of cotton from Savannah, Georgia
  - Money
    - 2 pieces of C.S.A. fractional currency 1862
      25 cents - County of Goochland; 50 cents - County of Goochland
    - 1 Virginia Treasury Note 1862